<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<atom:link href="undefined/undefined/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
<title>undefined</title>
<description>undefined</description>
<link>undefined</link>
<lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 02:36:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 02:36:02 GMT</pubDate>
<ttl>1440</ttl>
<item>
<title>A client-side Mahjong scoring app using React</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;2 weeks ago, on a Saturday, I thought I&amp;#39;d revisit my old &lt;a href="http://pomax.nihongoresources.com/downloads/mjscoring"&gt;PHP-based&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mahjong"&gt;mahjong&lt;/a&gt; scoring application. We like playing Chinese Classical rules, which are a little more &amp;quot;fun&amp;quot; and a little less &amp;quot;optimised for gambling&amp;quot; that the usual rules, and one aspect of that is that it&amp;#39;s much harder to track scores: everyone pays the winner, but the losers settle score differences amongst themselves in addition to paying the winner, too, and there&amp;#39;s a fair number of different things to score. Plus, you can get both points and &amp;quot;doubles&amp;quot;, the latter of which doubles (surprise!) your total point score. Only 28 tile points but 5 doubles? That&amp;#39;s 896 points total.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that fateful Saturday, I decided I&amp;#39;d put &lt;a href="https://www.polymer-project.org"&gt;Polymer&lt;/a&gt; to the test, and see if it&amp;#39;d hold up. I was doing my dev work in &lt;a href="http://www.sublimetext.com"&gt;Sublime Text 2&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/chrome"&gt;Chrome&lt;/a&gt;, and that combination worked just fine. And then after a day and a few hours on sunday, I tried it in &lt;a href="http://firefox.com"&gt;Firefox&lt;/a&gt;, and all my joy turned to hatred as the app broke all over the place. Polymer plain old didn&amp;#39;t work (and at this point, sad to say, Polymer is dead to me). The bits that did we slow, the bits that didn&amp;#39;t ultimately gave me too much of a headache trying to fix specifically for Firefox. I literally gave up: it was easy to port, too bad technology let me down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, as per the previous post, the Mozilla Foundation engineering team is considering using &lt;a href="http://facebook.github.io/react"&gt;React&lt;/a&gt;, and what better way to learn it than to take that broken Polymer app, and rewrite it as a React app? Long story short: a week later I ported the app from Polymer to React, and React works brilliantly in all browsers (yes, IE11 and Android 4.2 work) and is &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt; too boot. So... I have a new app up and running for scoring mahjong, and that makes me happy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://pomax.github.io/mjscoring.js"&gt;&lt;img src="gh-weblog/images/mjscoring-screenshot.jpg" class="border"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find it over on &lt;a href="http://pomax.github.io/mjscoring.js"&gt;http://pomax.github.io/mjscoring.js&lt;/a&gt;, with the source code living over on &lt;a href="https://github.com/pomax/mjscoring.js"&gt;github&lt;/a&gt; and I&amp;#39;ve been using it along side some games played in &lt;a href="https://www.4windsmj.com"&gt;Four Winds Mahjong&lt;/a&gt; (which may look old, but is still the best at actually seriously playing MJ that I know of) to see if the scoring holds up, and after some initial bug fixing, it feels like it&amp;#39;s doing just that. No more having to rely on a set of unmaintanable old PHP scripts anymore, and I even wrote it so that it&amp;#39;ll be relatively easy to add in new scoring rules, for when you prefer to play HK rules. Which can be nice sometimes, if you don&amp;#39;t want the cut-throat &amp;quot;I need to destroy you, you&amp;#39;re winning too much, but first I need to become east&amp;quot; excitement that Chinese Classical rules bring to the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<category>React</category>
<category>Mahjong</category>
<category>Games</category>
<link>undefined/#gh-weblog-1419403759737</link>
<guid>undefined/#gh-weblog-1419403759737</guid>
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Dec 2014 06:49:19 GMT</pubDate>
</item></channel>
</rss>
